Guide to the Harry S. Mosher Papers
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Harry S. Mosher papers
1944-2000
SC0645
Mosher, Harry S.
37.5 Linear feet
Papers include correspondence, manuscripts and reprints, research files, lab notebooks, grant files, and class materials.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Harry Mosher, 2002.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Harry S. Mosher earned his bachelor's degree in 1937 from Willamette University and his master's degree from Oregon State University in 1939. He taught briefly at Willamette before earning his doctorate in organic chemistry from Pennsylvania State University in 1942; he remained at Penn during World War II as an assistant professor supervising research on synthetic anti-malarial drugs for the National Research Council. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1947 and taught until his retirement in 1981. During his career at Stanford, Mosher taught organic chemistry and conducted research in a wide range of areas, including natural products chemistry and stereochemistry. He co-authored more than 140 research papers and a reference book titled ASYMMETRIC ORGANIC REACTIONS, published in 1971. Mosher also elucidated the chemical structure of tetrodotoxin - an extremely toxic molecule found in wild newts inhabiting Stanford's Lake Lagunita. Mosher died in March of 2001.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, manuscripts and reprints, research files, lab notebooks, grant files, and class materials.
Access Terms
Mosher, Harry S.; Chemistry, Organic.; Chemistry--Study and teaching (Higher).; Organic compounds --Synthesis.; Stereochemistry.; Tetrodotoxin.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-161
  - Research Students – correspondence, A – We (Box 1)
  - Research Students – correspondence, Wi – Wu (Box 2)
  - Publications & Bibliography (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1975 to present (Box 2)
  - Referee Reports (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts in preparation (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts in preparation (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts published (Box 3)
  - Post-Doc Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Post-Doc Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Post-Doc Correspondence (Ma – Z) (Box 5)
  - Miro's files re grants (Box 5)
  - Miro's files re grants (Box 6)
  - Files re: Analyses (Box 6)
  - Files re: Asymmetric Organic Reactions (Box 6)
  - Files re: Chemicals (Box 6)
  - Files re: Committees – Departmental University Regulations (Box 7)
  - Files re: Consulting (Box 7)
  - Files re: Equipment & Instruments (Box 7)
  - Files re: Enzymes (Box 7)
  - Files re: Examinations [one file = ACS CPT John Howard] (Box 7)
  - Files re: Isotopes (Box 7)
  - Files re: Lectures (Box 8)
  - Files re: Meetings & Travel (Box 8)
  - Files re: Meetings & Travel (Box 9)
  - Files re: Peroxides (Box 9)
  - Files re: Research Problems (Box 9)
  - Files re: Research Problems (Box 10)
  - Files re: Research Problems (Box 11)
  - Files re: Grignard Whitmore lect. (Box 11)
  - Files re: Grignard Whitmore lect. (Box 12)
  - Files re: Research techniques (Box 12)
  - Files re: Reviews (Box 12)
  - Files re: Sabbatical (Box 12)
  - Files re: Spectra (Box 12)
  - Files re: Synthetic Drugs (Box 12)
  - Files re: Synthetic Drugs (Box 13)
  - Files re: Toxins (Box 14)
  - Files re: Toxins (Box 15)
  - Files re: Tetrodotoxin (Box 15)
  - Files re: Tetrodotoxin (Box 16)
  - Files re: Tetrodotoxin (Box 17)
  - Research Files, spectra analysis (Box 17)
  - Research Files, spectra analysis (Box 18)
  - Reprints in chronological order, 1997-1987 (Box 18)
  - Reprints in chronological order, 1987-1950 (Box 19)
  - Reprints in chronological order, 1950-1944 (Box 20)
  - Lab notebooks (Box 21-23)
  - Student correspondence (alphabetical) (Box 24)
  - Post Doc correspondence 1976-1985 (Box 24)
  - Alpha files: Baxter -, 1950s-80s (Box 24)
  - Curriculum committee 1970s (Box 25)
  - Curricula 1975-2000 (Box 25)
  - Chemistry Department history – interview (Box 25)
  - ACS-CPT Directory stats (Box 25)
  - List of Post doc and Grad Students of Harry Mosher (Box 25)
  - Publications & Research plans (Box 25)
  - Research Problems & Plans selected (Box 25)
  - Research Problems General 1960-69 (Box 25)
  - Stanford Chemistry Alumni Newsletter 1988-91 (SCAN) (Box 25)
  - Potential Copy (Box 25)
  - Stereochemical (course) (Box 25)
  - Dynamic Stereo Chem (Box 25)
  - Asymmetric reductions (Box 25)
  - Asymm Syn 1978, 1976 (Box 25)
  - Stereochemistry Problems (Box 25)
  - Absolute Configurations (Box 25)
  - Asymm Syn Lit 1977-83 (Box 25)
  - Asymm Reactions Lit 1973 (Box 25)
  - Asym Syn 1970-72 (References) (Box 25)
  - Sulphur Stereochem (Box 25)
  - Asym Syn 1974-75, 1977 (Box 25)
  - Asym Chiral Hyro- (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 25)
  - Research notebooks (Mosher and students) (Box 26)
  - Several dissertations by students (Box 26)
  - Research notebooks (Mosher and students) (Box 27)
  - Research notebooks (Mosher and students) (Box 28)
  - Harry S. Mosher, Master's thesis, 1939 (Box 28)
  - Harry S. Mosher, "Research Reports, Aug. – Dec. 1940" (Box 28)
  - Harry S. Mosher, "Research Reports, 1941" (Box 28)
  - Harry S. Mosher, Ph.D. dissertation 1942 (Box 28)
  - Harry S. Moser, Confidential Report: Antimalarials: Natural and Synthetic, 1942 (Box 28)
  - Assorted glass slides for lectures (formulas, charts, models) (Box 29)
  - Two color 35mm slides of a molecular model, and 1 b/w negative (Box 29)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2003-225
  - Students' lab notebooks:
    - Janet S. Plummer, 2 v., 1988-90 (Box 1)
    - Yan Wang, 2 v., 1989-90 (Box 1)
    - Keekyung Kim, 1 v., 1986-87 (Box 1)
    - You Tian-pa, 3 v., 1983-85 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified author, 1 page filled, 5/26/82 (Box 1)
  - Harry S. Mosher notebooks, 3 v., 1954-78 (Box 1)
  - Carol W. Mosher notebook, 1 v., 1952-83 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Melancthon Starr, "Chemical Studies on Taricha Embryonic Toxin," Ph.D. thesis, Stanford, 1962 (carbon copy) (Box 1)
  - Nachman, Ronald James, "Synthetic Approaches to Tetrodotoxin and Analogs," Ph.D. thesis, Stanford, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Assorted student progress reports on research on Tetrodotoxin, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous reports, proposals, reprints, bibliographic notes by Mosher (Box 1)
  - Upestacis, J., "A Carbohydrate Approach to Tetrodotoxin," Harvard Ph.D. 1975 – printed from UMI microfilm (Box 1)
  - Sitrin, R., "Studies on the Synthesis of Tetrodotoxin," Harvard Ph.D. 1972 – printed from UMI microfilm (Box 1)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-176
  - SCAN (Stanford Chemistry Alumni Newsletter), 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Old Chemistry Wake (lecture and tour prior to closure of building), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eric Hutchinson "From Stillman to Parks, the early History of Chemistry at Stanford," text of talk for Old Chemistry Wake, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Slides used at Hutchinson's talk (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs from Old Chemistry Wake, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Old Chemistry – clippings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
General note
Collection is unprocessed and in remote storage. For access, please contact the University Archivist.